#大家好 今天我們炒點這個燙皮來吃 (註︰這個「炒」應該不能用"fry"，我見香港的「炒栗子」多數叫"Roasted Chesnuts"，所以也用"roast"吧)
Hi everyone! We wanna make roast "tang pi" today.
#這個燙皮還是去年做的
The "tang pi" were prepared last year.
#現在放了這麼久了
It has been quite a while since then.
我先把它曬一下再來 再來炒
Let me dry them under the sun, before, before roasting them.
#剛好這裡有一塊平地
The flat bench here is just right.
#要先把這個燙皮先曬一曬
The "tang pi" need to be put under the sun first.
#因為
Cuz,
#因為放到袋子裡面它都
they're soaked after being in the bag,
#回潮啦
for a long time.
#我們曬一下的話就
They can be more easily roasted,
#更容易炒的[SIC]出來
after being dried,
#更好炒
much easier.
#先把它曬
Dry them,
#曬大片的
the larger ones.
#小片的不要
I don't want the small ones.
#擺的整整齊齊
Arrange them tidily.
#剩下的下次來
The rest is for the next time.
#它這個一次
It's not a good idea to make too many,
#一次不要全部炒完啦
too many at a time.
#想吃的時候就直接拿出來炒
I can simply roast some whenever I wanna eat.
#我們去河邊搞點那個沙子上來
We're going to get some sand from the riverside.
#小狗 走 (註︰狗都那麼大了，他還叫「小狗」，我譯不出"puppy"了，同樣之後的「小豬」也是)
Doggies! Let's go!
#走
Go!
#你看 下面有沙哦
Look! There's sand down there.
#一起去
Let's go together,
#搞一點來
to get some.
#你看 我把這個漏
Look! I use the col,
#漏子啊
colander,
#過濾一下這個沙子
to filtrate the sand.
#過濾出來的就是粗沙
Only the coarse sand remains after filtrating.
#一下不能搞那麼多 太多了過濾不了
Not too much at a time. You just can't do it well with too much sand.
#應該可以了
Should be alright.
#我 我們要 要這個粗一點的沙子 不要那個細沙
We, we need the, the coarser sand, not the fine one.
#等下我們再洗一下
We'll wash the sand in a minute.
#搞好啦
Alright!
#一飄盆 (註︰這是何解？)
A whole bucket.
#我們洗一下
Let's wash it.
#好啦 洗好啦
Alright!
#我們回去把這個沙子先
Let's first dry the sand,
#炒乾水
in a hot wok.
#等下再來炒那個燙皮
Then it can be used to roast the "tang pi".
#小狗
Doggies!
#回家咯
Time to go home!
#現在快下雨咯
It's gonna rain soon.
#我把那個燙皮收一下
I'll get back the "tang pi".
#等一下 一下雨
Otherwise, if it rains,
#燙皮就沒用了
game over.
#那兩個狗在打架
Those two dogs are having a fight.
#把它收到這個 筐裡面裝
Get them back, into this basket.
#好啦 你看 收回來啦
Alright. Look! They're all here now.
#嗯 有點味道 (註︰不知他想說是香還是臭，不管了)
Um! I can smell something.
#先放點油哦
Put some oil,
#放到鍋裡 (註︰他這個鍋在我們廣東話多數叫「鑊」，所以我用了"wok")
into the wok first.
#鍋邊上 澆點油
Spill some oil, onto the rim.
#還有水
There's still some moisture.
#要把水炒乾
I need to dry it completely.
#剛才加了點油下去啊 要把這個油 燒熱才可以
I've just put some oil. I need to wait, until the, the oil gets heated.
#這個沙都黑了 應該可以炒啦
The sand is now dark. It could be used for roasting now.
#用這個沙的溫度 把它崩起來 (註︰甚麼是「崩起來」？)
The temperature of the sand will develop the "tang pi".
#大熱啦這裡 叫我弟過來炒
It's too hot here. So I make my younger brother do it for me.
#教會他來 教會他來我們就不用幹
I'll teacher him. Then we can leave the rest to him.
#就這樣炒 (註︰其實我不清楚這句是村霸還是弟弟說的)
That's how you should roast them.
#你會啊
You know how?
#要快一點
Faster!
#沙子溫度很高的
The temperature of the sand is really high.
#好 翻一下
Alright! Flip it.
#翻起來
Flip it.
#翻面了 沙子鋪緊
To the other side. Cover it with sand!
#還說你會
And you said you know how.
#都不知道怎麼燒
See what you are going?
#不是嗎 (註︰我好像聽到他說「唔喺咩」)
What's wrong?
#弟弟
Brother,
#弟弟都會炒 讓他來炒一下
now my brother can do it. It's his turn now.
#我到外面喘口氣
I'll take a breath outside.
#好熱哦
It's far too hot.
#你看那個豬
Look at that pig.
#好爽哦
It's having a good time,
#趴在那個水上
lying in the water.
#等一下我抓起來秤一下
Let me see if I can catch it and weigh it.
#現在它胖了好多啊
It's now much fatter than it was.
#我們用洗手池
The pond is for washing our hands,
#這豬就跑下去洗澡
and now the pig is having a bath here.
#這樣下去不行的哦
It will be a problem.
#小豬
Piggy!
#游泳好不好玩
Do you enjoy swimming?
#好不好玩
Do you?
#我好不容易親自砌的哦 就被你拱掉啦
Do you know how much effort I've put into building the pond? And now you're ruining it.
#跑啦
It ran away.
#嚇跑了
I scared it away.
#拿 拿東西把它 把它抓起來
Catch, catch it with, with something.
#太聰明了
It's too clever.
#豬都那麼聰明
How can a pig be that clever?
#小豬
Piggy!
#給你好吃的要不要啊
I have some good food here. Do you want it?
#要不要啊 很好吃的
Do you? You will like it.
#我去會點玉米粒把它騙下來
Let me get some corns and see if I can nobble it.
#不然抓不住啊 這樣
I can't catch it, otherwise.
#來了吧
So you are coming.
#小狗你們湊甚麼熱鬧
Why are you crowding in doggies?
#這個你們又不吃
You guys never like the corns.
#豬才吃
Only the pigs eat them.
#多吃點啊 看能不能 長一斤
Eat more! See if you can, put on a pound.
#又跑 又跑
You run again! Again!
#你跑得過我嗎
You think you can run faster than me?
#抓不到啦現在 它這小豬比狗跑的還快
I don't think I can catch it now. That piggy runs even fast than the dogs.
#搞得我氣都喘不過來啦
I'm panting like a horse.
#順著方向跑到那山上去啦
It runs all the way up to the hill.
#不管它
Leave it alone.
#它晚上會回家的
It will come back at night.
#因為它山上找不到吃的
There's nothing for it to eat on the hill.
#自然會找我
It can only come back to me.
#終於炒好了
It's done, finally.
#味道
It tastes,
#味道很不錯哦
it tastes really not bad.
#很脆
Crispy.
#這個我們這邊的
It's kind of,
#這邊 好像這邊的才會做這個特產的
it's kind of a specialty that is only made in this region.
#這個叫燙皮
It's called "tang pi".
#我們普通話叫 "kolei"
It's called "kolei" in our mandarin.
#我們的客家話 不是普通話啊
I mean in our Hakka dialect, not mandarin.
#"kolei"
"Kolei",
#又叫"lalei"
or "lalei".
#很香的
It smells good.
#逢年過節
During festivals,
#反正就
or whatever kind of,
#喜 額 那個甚麼 喜事啊 那些 都會吃這個
cele, eh, what is it, celebrations, it always has a place.
#這個普通話叫燙皮
So it's called "tang pi" in mandarin.
#好啦
Alright!
#今天的視頻到這裡啦
The video ends here.
#這個 打包
I'll take away,
#打包回去給家人吃
bring it home for my family.
#我一個人吃不完的
I can't finish it alone.
#嗯 好香
Um! It smells so good.
#我要用那個尼龍袋把它紥起來
I'll tie them up in a bag,
#它就不會軟掉
so they won't get softened.